<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>RNAseq on BMMB554</title>
    <link>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/tags/rnaseq/</link>
    <description>Recent content in RNAseq on BMMB554</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/tags/rnaseq/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of RNA II: RiboSeq, and other things</title>
      <link>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/lecture12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/lecture12/</guid>
      <description>Potentially interesting sites This only works for PSU-based people  Open this spreadsheet.
It has the following columns:
 Group: People, to whom variants are assigned Sample: SRA accession CHROM: Reference genome (same for all rows) POS: Position of the variant in the genome (1-based) REF: Reference allele ALT: Alternative allele DP: Read depth AF: Alternative allele frequency SB: Strand bias as calculated by lofreq (0 = no strand bias) DP4: Strand-specific depth for reference and alternate allele observations (Forward reference, reverse reference, forward alternate, reverse alternate) IMPACT: functional impact of the substitution FUNCLASS: type of change EFFECT: effect of the change GENE: gene name CODON: codon type: type of variant (S = SNP, I = Indel, M = MNP ) GENE: gene name SITE: codon within the gene FEL: Is site identified by FEL as being under selection MEME: Is site identified by MEME as being under selection MEME.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of RNA I: Molecular Biology of SARS-COV-2</title>
      <link>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/lecture11/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/lecture11/</guid>
      <description>A quick overview of coronavirus molecular biology Given the current situation we will continue this class using SARS-COV-2 as example for all further analyses. So far we have covered variant calling and genome assembly. Next we will be looking into RNAseq. Since SARS-COV-2 is a positive strand RNA virus that pretends to be a typical human transcript, it is a great system to learn about RNAseq. But first we need to learn about the coronavirus molecular biology.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>