<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>python on BMMB554</title>
    <link>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/tags/python/</link>
    <description>Recent content in python on BMMB554</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/tags/python/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Lecture 7: Plotting in Python</title>
      <link>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/lecture8/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/lecture8/</guid>
      <description>This lecture draws extensively from Seaborn tutorials.  A primer of plotting with Python # If running in colaboratory uncomment and run the folliwing command pip install seaborn --upgrade pip install pysqldf from pandasql import sqldf pysqldf = lambda q: sqldf(q, globals()) import seaborn as sns sns.set(style=&amp;#34;ticks&amp;#34;) import pandas as pd import matplotlib.pyplot as plt Why plotting? We will use Ascombe&#39;s quartet build into Seaborn to answer this questions
# Load the example dataset for Anscombe&amp;#39;s quartet df = sns.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lecture 3: Defining project and getting data</title>
      <link>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/lecture3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/lecture3/</guid>
      <description>WarmUp with Python Strings  Open this notebook Make a copy of it in your drive Go through it and execute all cells  The project The goal of our project will be finding a perfect variant caller for non-diploid data (e.g., viral, bacterial, organellar).
For this we will use two datasets:
 An HIV resequencing data from the DC cohort study A duplex sequencing dataset from an experimental evolution study  The idea is to use duplex data as the &amp;ldquo;golden standard&amp;rdquo; and then apply the best caller we find to HIV data and see if we can find anything interesting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lecture 1: Basic machinery = Jupyter &#43; Python</title>
      <link>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/lecture1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/lecture1/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to Notebooks An important assumption for this lecture is that (1) you have a Google account, (2) know how to use Google Drive, and (3) also have an active GitHub account.  When you start an analysis, you don&#39;t really know how it will go. Maybe data is bad and there is no real reason to analyze anything at all. Maybe data data outliers that need to be dealt with.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>