<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>BMMB554 | Fall 2017</title>
    <link>http://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on BMMB554 | Fall 2017</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Released under the MIT license&lt;br&gt;Powered by [Hugo](//gohugo.io/) with the [Type Theme](//github.com/digitalcraftsman/hugo-type-theme)</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2017 11:17:20 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>DNA sequencing</title>
      <link>http://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/post/topic2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2017 11:17:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/post/topic2/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-60s-and-the-70s&#34;&gt;The 60s and the 70s&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first complete nucleic acids being sequenced were RNAs (tRNAs in particular; see pioneering work of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/14263761&#34;&gt;Robert Holley and colleagues&lt;/a&gt;). The work on finding approaches to sequencing DNA molecules began in late 60s and early 70s. One of the earliest contributions has been made by Ray Wu from Cornell, who used &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; DNA polymerase to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/0022283670900045&#34;&gt;incorporate radioactively labelled nucleotides into protruding ends of bacteriphage lambda&lt;/a&gt;. It took several more years for the development of more &amp;ldquo;high throughput&amp;rdquo; technologies by Sanger and Maxam/Gilbert. The Sanger technique has ultimately won over Maxam/Gilbert&amp;rsquo;s protocol due to its relative simplicity (once dideoxynucleotides has become commercially available) and the fact that it required smaller amount of starting material as the polymerase was used to generate fragments necessary for sequence determination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;original-approaches-were-laborious&#34;&gt;Original approaches were laborious&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the original &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC431765/pdf/pnas00043-0271.pdf&#34;&gt;Sanger paper&lt;/a&gt; the authors sequenced bacteriophage phiX174 by using its own restriction fragments as primers. This was an ideal set up to show the proof of principle for the new method. This is because phiX174 DNA is homogeneous and can be isolated in large quantities. Now suppose that you would like to sequence a larger genome (say &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt;). Remember that the original version of Sanger method can only sequence fragments up to 200 nucleotides at a time. So to sequence the entire &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; genome (which by-the-way was not sequenced until &lt;a href=&#34;http://science.sciencemag.org/content/277/5331/1453&#34;&gt;1997&lt;/a&gt;) you would need to split the genome into multiple pieces and sequence each of them individually. This is hard, because to produce a readable Sanger sequencing gel each sequence must be amplified to a suitable amount (around 1 nanogram) and be homogeneous (you cannot mix multiple DNA fragments in a single reaction as it will be impossible to interpret the gel). Molecular cloning enabled by the availability of commercially available restriction enzymes and cloning vectors simplified this process. Until the onset of next generation sequencing in 2005 the process for sequencing looked something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt;) - Generate a collection of fragments you want to sequence. It can be a collection of fragments from a genome that was mechanically sheared or just a single fragment generated by PCR.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt;) - These fragment(s) are then cloned into a plasmid vector (we will talk about other types of vectors such as BACs later in the course).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;3&lt;/strong&gt;) - Vectors are transformed into bacterial cells and positive colonies (containing vectors with insert) are picked from an agar plate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;4&lt;/strong&gt;) - Each colony now represents a unique piece of DNA.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;5&lt;/strong&gt;) - An individual colony is used to seed a bacterial culture that is grown overnight.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;6&lt;/strong&gt;) - Plasmid DNA is isolated from this culture and now can be used for sequencing because it is (1) homogeneous and (2) we now a sufficient amount.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;7&lt;/strong&gt;) - It is sequenced using universal primers. For example the image below shows a map for pGEM-3Z plasmid (a pUC18 derivative). Its multiple cloning site is enlarged and sites for &lt;strong&gt;T7&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;SP6&lt;/strong&gt; sequencing primers are shown. These are the &lt;strong&gt;pads&lt;/strong&gt; I&amp;rsquo;m referring to in the lecture. These provide universal sites that can be used to sequence any insert in between.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/BMMB554/img/pgem3z.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

Figure from Promega, Inc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until the invention of NGS the above protocol was followed with some degree of automation. But you can see that it was quite laborious if the large number of fragements needed to be sequenced. This is because each of them needed to be subcloned and handled separately. This is in part why Human Genome Project, a subject of our next lecture, took so much time to complete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;evolution-of-sequencing-machines&#34;&gt;Evolution of sequencing machines&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simplest possible sequencing machine is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polyacrylamide_gel_electrophoresis&#34;&gt;gel rig with polyacrylamide gel&lt;/a&gt;. Sanger used it is his protocol obtaining the following results:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/BMMB554/img/sangerGel.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

Figure from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC431765/pdf/pnas00043-0271.pdf&#34;&gt;Sanger et al. 1977&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here for sequencing each fragment four separate reactions are peformed (with ddA, ddT, ggC, and ddG) and four lanes on the gel are used. One simplification of this process that came in the 90s was to use fluorescently labelled dideoxy nucleotides. This is easier because everything can be performed in a single tube and uses a single lane on a gel:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/BMMB554/img/dd_labels.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

Figure from Applied Biosystems &lt;a href=&#34;https://www3.appliedbiosystems.com/cms/groups/mcb_support/documents/generaldocuments/cms_041003.pdf&#34;&gt;support site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there is still substantial labor involved in pouring the gels, loading them, running machines, and cleaning everything post-run. A significant improvement was offered by the development of capillary electrophoresis allowing automation of liquid handling and sample loading. Although several manufacturers have been developing and selling such machines a &lt;em&gt;de facto&lt;/em&gt; standard in this area was (and still is) the Applied Biosystems (ABI) Genetics and DNA Anlayzer systems. The highest throughput ABI system, 3730&lt;em&gt;xl&lt;/em&gt;, had 96 capillaries and could automatically process 384 samples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;ngs&#34;&gt;NGS!&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;384 samples may sound like a lot, but it is nothing if we are sequencing an entire genome. The beauty of NGS is that these technologies are not bound by sample handling logistics. They still require preparation of libraries, but once a library is made (which can be automated) it is processed more or less automatically to generate multiple copies of each fragment (in the case of 454, Illumina, and Ion Torrent) and loaded onto the machine, where millions of individual fragments are sequenced simultaneously. The following videos and slides explains how these technologies work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-introductory-video&#34;&gt;Watch introductory video&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//player.vimeo.com/video/181072208&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h1 id=&#34;ngs-in-depth&#34;&gt;NGS in depth&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-454-sequencing&#34;&gt;1: 454 sequencing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;454 Technology is a massively parallel modification of &lt;a href=&#34;http://genome.cshlp.org/content/11/1/3&#34;&gt;pyrosequencing&lt;/a&gt; technology. Incorporation of nucleotides are registered by a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charge-coupled_device&#34;&gt;CCD&lt;/a&gt; camera as a flash of light generated from the interaction between ATP and Luciferin. The massive scale of 454 process is enabled by generation of a population of beads carrying multiple copies of the same DNA fragment. The beads are distributed across a microtiter plate where each well of the plate holding just one bead. Thus every unique coordinate (a well) on the plate generates flashes when a nucleotide incorporation event takes plate. This is &amp;ldquo;monochrome&amp;rdquo; technique: flash = nucleotide is incorporated; lack of flash = no incorporation. Thus to distinguish between A, C, G, and T individual nucleotides are &amp;ldquo;washed&amp;rdquo; across the microtiter plate at discrete times: if &lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt; is being washed across the plate and a flash of light is emitted, this implies that A is present in the fragment being sequenced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;454 can generated fragments up 1,000 bases in length. Its biggest weakness is inability to precisely determine the length of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.broadinstitute.org/crd/wiki/index.php/Homopolymer&#34;&gt;homopolymer runs&lt;/a&gt;. Thus the main type if sequencing error generated by 454 are insertions and deletions (indels).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;slides&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;script async class=&#39;speakerdeck-embed&#39; data-id=&#39;28bd628499b54d09b4f9c6e7534c7e8f&#39; data-ratio=&#39;1.33333333333333&#39; src=&#39;//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//player.vimeo.com/video/121286060&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Underlying slides are &lt;a href=&#34;https://speakerdeck.com/nekrut/ngs-technologies-454#&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reading&#34;&gt;Reading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2001 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://genome.cshlp.org/content/11/1/3&#34;&gt;Overview of pyrosequencing methodology - Ronaghi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2005 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v437/n7057/pdf/nature03959.pdf&#34;&gt;Description of 454 process - Margulies et al.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2007 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://link.springer.com/protocol/10.1385/1-59745-377-3:1&#34;&gt;History of pyrosequencing - Pål Nyrén&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2007 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://genomebiology.com/content/pdf/gb-2007-8-7-r143.pdf&#34;&gt;Errors in 454 data - Huse et al. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2010 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/content/26/18/i420.full.pdf+html&#34;&gt;Properties of 454 data - Balzer et al.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-illumina-sequencing&#34;&gt;2: Illumina sequencing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Illumina (originally called &amp;ldquo;Solexa&amp;rdquo;) uses glass flowcells with oligonucleotides permanently attached to internal surface. These oligonucleotides are complementary to sequencing adapters added to DNA fragments being sequenced during library preparation. The DNA fragements that are &amp;ldquo;stuck&amp;rdquo; on the flowcell due to complementary interaction between adapters are amplified via &amp;ldquo;bridge amplification&amp;rdquo; to form clusters. Sequencing is performed using reversible terminator chemistry with nucleotides modified to carry dyes specific to each nucleotide. As a result all nucleotides can be added at once and are distinguished by colors. Currently, it is possible to sequence up to 300 bases from each end of the fragment being sequenced. Illumina has the highest throughput (and lowest cost per base) of all existing technologies at this moment. The HiSeq 2500 machine can produce &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.illumina.com/systems/hiseq_2500_1500/performance_specifications.html&#34;&gt;600 billion nucleotides in 5 days&lt;/a&gt;. In this course we will most often work with Illumina data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;slides-1&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;script async class=&#39;speakerdeck-embed&#39; data-id=&#39;942908c8c24546d58cf8b61b3598feb3&#39; data-ratio=&#39;1.33333333333333&#39; src=&#39;//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;video-1&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//player.vimeo.com/video/121178846&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Underlying slides are &lt;a href=&#34;https://speakerdeck.com/nekrut/ngs-technologies-illumina#&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;reading-1&#34;&gt;Reading&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2008 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v456/n7218/pdf/nature07517.pdf&#34;&gt;Human genome sequencing on Illumina - Bentley et al.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2010 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/content/39/13/e90.full-text-lowres.pdf&#34;&gt;Data quality 1 - Nakamura et al.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2011 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://genomebiology.com/content/pdf/gb-2011-12-11-r112.pdf&#34;&gt;Data quality 2 - Minoche et al.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2011 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biomedcentral.com/content/pdf/1471-2164-12-382.pdf&#34;&gt;Illumina pitfalls - Kircher et al.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-pacbio-single-molecule-sequencing&#34;&gt;3: PacBio Single Molecule Sequencing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PacBio is a fundamentally different approach to DNA sequencing as it allows reading single molecules. Thus it is an example is so called &lt;em&gt;Single Molecule Sequencing&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;SMS&lt;/em&gt;. PacBio uses highly processive DNA polymerase placed at the bottom of each well on a microtiter plate. The plate is fused to the glass slide illuminated by a laser. When polymerase is loaded with template it attracts fluorescently labeled nucleotides to the bottom of the well where they emit light with a wavelength characteristic of each nucleotide. As a result a &amp;ldquo;movie&amp;rdquo; is generated for each well recording the sequence and duration of incorporation events. One of the key advantage of PacBio technology is its ability to produce long reads with ones at 10,000 bases being common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;slides-2&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;script async class=&#39;speakerdeck-embed&#39; data-id=&#39;ccb3d34f1a214f66ac7a2d233caedaf5&#39; data-ratio=&#39;1.33333333333333&#39; src=&#39;//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;video-2&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//player.vimeo.com/video/121267426&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Underlying slides are &lt;a href=&#34;https://speakerdeck.com/nekrut/ngs-technologies-pacific-biosceinces&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;reading-2&#34;&gt;Reading&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2003 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencemag.org/content/299/5607/682.full.pdf&#34;&gt;Single Molecule Analaysis at High Concentration - Levene et al.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2008 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pnas.org/content/105/4/1176.full&#34;&gt;ZMW nanostructures - Korlach et al.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2009 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencemag.org/content/323/5910/133.full&#34;&gt;Real Time Sequencing with PacBio - Eid et al.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2010 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/nmeth/journal/v7/n6/pdf/nmeth.1459.pdf&#34;&gt;Modification detection with PacBio - Flusberg et al.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2012 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/nbt/journal/v30/n7/pdf/nbt.2280.pdf&#34;&gt;Error correction of PacBio reads - Koren et al.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2014 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.1400447111&#34;&gt;Transcriptome with PacBio - Taligner et al.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2015 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature13907&#34;&gt;Resolving complex regions in Human genomes with PacBio - Chaisson et al.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;4-oxford-nanopore&#34;&gt;4: Oxford Nanopore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oxford nanopore is another dramatically different technology that threads single DNA molecules through biologically-derived (transmembrane proteins) pore in a membrane impermeable to ions. It uses polymerase to control the speed of translocation of the DNA molecule through membrane. In that sense it is not &lt;em&gt;Sequencing by synthesis&lt;/em&gt; we have seen in the other technologies discussed here. This technology generates longest reads possible today: in many instances a single read can be hundreds of thousands if nucleotides in length. It still however suffers from high error rate and relatively low throughput (compared to Illumina). On the upside Oxford Nanopore sequencing machines are only slightly bigger than a thumb-drive and cost very little.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;slides-3&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;script async class=&#39;speakerdeck-embed&#39; data-id=&#39;3895a3069bc64ad5bc74c972a0353911&#39; data-ratio=&#39;1.33333333333333&#39; src=&#39;//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent overview of latest developments at Oxford Nanopore can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lmmx/talk-transcripts/blob/master/Nanopore/NoThanksIveAlreadyGotOne.md&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; as well as in the following video&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/nizGyutn6v4&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;reading-3&#34;&gt;Reading&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://nature.com/nnano/journal/v11/n2/full/nnano.2016.9.html&#34;&gt;The promises and challenges of solid-state sequencing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2015 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://nature.com/nmeth/journal/v12/n4/full/nmeth.3290.html&#34;&gt;Improved data analysis for the minion nanopore sequencer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2015 | &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4722697/&#34;&gt;MinION Analysis and Reference Consortium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2015 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/nmeth/journal/v12/n8/full/nmeth.3444.html&#34;&gt;A complete bacterial genome assembled &lt;em&gt;de novo&lt;/em&gt; using only nanopore sequencing data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2012 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://nature.com/nbt/journal/v30/n4/full/nbt.2171.html&#34;&gt;Reading DNA at single-nucleotide resolution with a mutant MspA nanopore and phi29 DNA polymerase&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simpson Lab &lt;a href=&#34;http://simpsonlab.github.io/2015/04/08/eventalign/&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Poretools analysis &lt;a href=&#34;http://poretools.readthedocs.org/&#34;&gt;suite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>History</title>
      <link>http://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/post/topic1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 11:41:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/post/topic1/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;why-history&#34;&gt;Why history?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowing history is essential for understanding how we arrived to the current state of affairs in our field. It is also full of acciental discoveries and dramatic relationships making it quite interesting to read about. I strongly advise you to take a look at the mansucripts below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;classical-publications&#34;&gt;Classical publications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1965 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/A-History-Genetics-A-H-Sturtevant/dp/0879696079&#34;&gt;A history of genetics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1943 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bx.psu.edu/~anton/bioinf1-2014/delbruck-luria-1943.pdf&#34;&gt;Delbruck &amp;amp; Luria&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1944 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bx.psu.edu/~anton/bioinf1-2014/avery-1944.pdf&#34;&gt;Avery, MacLeod, &amp;amp; McCarty&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1952 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bx.psu.edu/~anton/bioinf1-2014/hershey-chase-1952.pdf&#34;&gt;Herhey &amp;amp; Chase&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1953 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bx.psu.edu/~anton/bioinf1-2014/watsoncrick.pdf&#34;&gt;Watson &amp;amp; Crick&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1958 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bx.psu.edu/~anton/bioinf1-2014/Proc%20Natl%20Acad%20Sci%20USA%201958%20Meselson.pdf&#34;&gt;Meselson &amp;amp; Stahl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1960 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bx.psu.edu/~anton/bioinf1-2014/jacob-monod-1961.pdf&#34;&gt;Jacob and Monod&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;popular-yet-very-informative-literature&#34;&gt;Popular (yet very informative) literature&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get one of these and read it on a plane:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1978 | &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Molecular-Genetics-Introductory-Gunther-Stent/dp/0716700484&#34;&gt;Molecular Gemetics: An Itroductory Narrative&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2001 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/The-Double-Helix-Discovery-Structure/dp/074321630X&#34;&gt;The double helix&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2005 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Third-Man-Double-Helix-Autobiography/dp/019280667X&#34;&gt;The Third Man of the Double Helix&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2014 | &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Brave-Genius-Philosopher-Adventures-Resistance/dp/0307952347&#34;&gt;Brave Genius&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;publication-highlight-the-fluctuation-test&#34;&gt;Publication highlight | The fluctuation test&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a truly collaborative spirit a german physicist &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/medicine/laureates/1969/delbruck-facts.html&#34;&gt;Max Delbrück&lt;/a&gt; joined forces with an italian microbiologist &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/medicine/laureates/1969/luria-facts.html&#34;&gt;Salvador Luria&lt;/a&gt; to prove the stochastic nature of mutations and to reject &amp;ldquo;the last stroghold of Lamarckism&amp;rdquo;. This &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bx.psu.edu/~anton/bioinf1-2014/delbruck-luria-1943.pdf&#34;&gt;classical work&lt;/a&gt; was published in 1943 in journal &lt;em&gt;Genetics&lt;/em&gt;. Here we re-examine some of the fundamental aspects of this work. In this we occasionally rely on a classical textbook in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Molecular-Genetics-Introductory-Gunther-Stent/dp/0716700484&#34;&gt;Molecular Genetics&lt;/a&gt; by Günther Stent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, it has been know for some time that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bacteria sensitive (infectable) by phage becomes resistant as a result of exposure to bacteriophage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The resistance is preserved when descendants of these cells are incubated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can, in principle, be explained by two mutually exclusive hypotheses:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;acquired-resistance-vs-spontaneous-mutation&#34;&gt;Acquired resistance vs. spontaneous mutation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;direct action of phage on bacteria triggers &amp;ldquo;acquisition&amp;rdquo; of the resistance;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;some cells in a population already have a mutation conferring the resistance and the exposure to the phage merely brings carriers of such mutations to prominence by killing off all sensitive cells.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we distinguish between these two alternative possibilities? Let&amp;rsquo;s try to put hypothesis (1) into quantitative framework:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are two bacterial phenotypes: &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt; - sensitive (is lysed by the phage) and &lt;em&gt;R&lt;/em&gt; - resistant (is not lysed and does not absorb phage)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bacterial population progresses from a single cell to $N$ cells&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The probability of changing from &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;R&lt;/em&gt; is $a$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if one grows $S$ bacteria in a culture and then plates them on agar containing excess of phage, where will be $n$ of $R$ colonies, where $n =  aN$. Since we can estimate $n$ directly (by counting colonies on the plate) and $N$ is also known (a function of the number of generations) the fraction of $R$ individuals in a population is going to be same for all stages of the population:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
$$

\frac{n}{N} = a

$$
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will not be quite the same for hypothesis (2) since the number of cells carrying the resistance mutation will differ depending on when in population history they occurred and how many generation have passed since their occurrence. After $g$ generations there will be&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
$$

N = 2^g

$$
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;cells. Consequently, if the probability of mutation is $a$, then by $i$-th generation there will be $a2^i$ cells carrying mutations and we can arrive to the ratio of&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
$$

\frac{n}{N} = ga

$$
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delbück and Luria&amp;rsquo;s experience with estimating such ratio has proven to be difficult as they were observing great fluctuation in the number of $R$ cells. They have subsequently realized that such fluctuation was in fact an indirect indication that the mutation hypothesis is likely true. Delbrück has developed a theoretical framework predicting the distribution of mutant phenotypes for both hypotheses. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Molecular-Genetics-Introductory-Gunther-Stent/dp/0716700484&#34;&gt;Stent&lt;/a&gt; provides the following elegant description of Delbück&amp;rsquo;s reasonong. It is based on measuring the variance in the number of resistant colonies across a number of replicates. Suppose there are $c$ &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; replicates (cultures) started from a single &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt; bacterium. Each is grown for $g$ generations, and each accumulates $N = 2^g$ cells as a result. The entire content of each culture is then spread over agar plate saturated with the phage. The number $n$ of &lt;em&gt;R&lt;/em&gt; colonies is then counted. If $n_j$ is the number of &lt;em&gt;R&lt;/em&gt; colonies from culture $j$, then the average of the numbner of resistant colonies is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
$$

\bar{n} = \frac{\sum_{j=1}^{c}n_j}{c}

$$
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and the variance is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
$$ 

var_n = \frac{\sum_{j=1}^{c}(\bar{n}-n_j)}{c}

$$
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The behaviour of ratio of &lt;code&gt;variance/average&lt;/code&gt; is critical to distinguishing between hypothesis (1) and (2). If (1) is true we expect low fluctuation and the ratio will be close to 1. If (2) is true the variation will be considerable and the ratio will be much higher than one. Look at Fig. 1 below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In pane A (Hypothesis 1) phage induces changes in the bacteria upon plating and because the probability of changing from &lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; is the same for  all cells we would see approximately the same number of &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; cells. The mean here is &lt;code&gt;2.5&lt;/code&gt; and the variance/mean ratio is &lt;code&gt;1.1&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In pane B (Hypothesis 2) every cell has the same mutation rate, but the mutations may occur at any point during the culture propagation. If they occur early - many resistant colonies will be produced from such culture. If they occur late - just a few. As a result one would expect to see significant fluctuation. Here the mean is the same as in A = &lt;code&gt;2.5&lt;/code&gt;, but the variance/mean ratio is much higher at &lt;code&gt;4.3&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/BMMB554/img/luria.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/BMMB554/img/stent.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1&lt;/strong&gt; (Fig. 6-4 from Stent)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table 1&lt;/strong&gt; (Table 6-1 from Stent)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table 1 settles these issues. Here one can see a significant fluctuation across 20 independent experiments with the main of &lt;code&gt;11.3&lt;/code&gt; and variance/mean ratio of &lt;code&gt;61&lt;/code&gt;. This table also show the result of plating aliquots from a bulk culture. In this case 10 ml culture was incubated for the same duration as the 20 independent cultures. Small amount from this culture were then plated on 10 independent plates. Because these cells share their genetic ancestry there is very little variation across these platings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper settled one of the most contentious issues in biology and won the Nobel prize to its authors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;slides&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slides covering material for Lecture 1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script async class=&#39;speakerdeck-embed&#39; data-id=&#39;7726e8b8b3ee41f0a2a1497128d59ca0&#39; data-ratio=&#39;1.33333333333333&#39; src=&#39;//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video presentation from last year.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//player.vimeo.com/video/180735569&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;


&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-vto-do-before-next-lecture&#34;&gt;What vto do before next lecture&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read two following papers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;DNA sequencing with chain-terminating inhibitors&amp;rdquo; by Sanger, Nicklen, and Coulson (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC431765/pdf/pnas00043-0271.pdf&#34;&gt;1977&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;A new method for sequencing DNA&amp;rdquo; by Maxam and Gilbert (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC392330/pdf/pnas00024-0174.pdf&#34;&gt;1977&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Syllabus</title>
      <link>http://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/about/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://xkcd.com/451/&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/impostor.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;instructor&#34;&gt;Instructor&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anton Nekrutenko&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:aun1@psu.edu?Subject=BMMB554&#34;&gt;aun1@psu.edu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Wartik 505&lt;br&gt;
Office hours by appointment only&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;font color=&#34;orange&#34;&gt;&amp;#9888;&lt;/font&gt; When contacting instructor use the above e-mail and include &amp;ldquo;BMMB554&amp;rdquo; in the subject line (simply click on e-mail address).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;course-description&#34;&gt;Course description&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This course is designed as a preparation routine for graduate students in Life Sciences. It has several focus areas including evolution of life sciences as well as in-depth overview of sequencing technologies and their applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;grading&#34;&gt;Grading&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Homework = 50%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Final project = 50%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;topics&#34;&gt;Topics&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will cover a breadth of topics. Below is the approximate list. Keep in mind that this field is very dynamic. To account for that we may skip or extend some of the subjects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;History: From Genetics to Genomics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sequencing: From Sanger to Nanopores I&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sequencing: From Sanger to Nanopores II&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Algorithms: Alignment Basics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Algorithms: Aligning many sequences quickly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Algorithms: Assembly I&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Algorithms: Assembly II&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Galaxy: An introduction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Galaxy: Writing your own tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Re-sequencing I: Introduction and non-diploid case&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Re-sequencing II: Diploid genomes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Practicum: Re-sequencing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transcriptomics I: Refrence-based&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transcriptomics II: Reference-free&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Practicum: Transcriptomics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RNA analysis: RiboSeq and ShapeSeq&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Practicum: RNA analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DNA/Protein interactions I: Approaches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DNA/Protein interactions II: ENCODE Project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Practicum: DNA/Protein interactions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Genome conformation analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Practicum: Genome conformation analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Metagenomics I: Approaches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Metagenomics II: Community analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Practicum: Metagenomics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an examination setting, unless the instructor gives explicit prior instructions to the contrary, violations of academic integrity shall consist of any attempt to receive assistance from written or printed aids, from any person or papers or electronic devices, or of any attempt to give assistance, whether the student doing so has completed his or her own work or not. Other violations include, but are not limited to, any attempt to gain an unfair advantage in regard to an examination, such as tampering with a graded exam or claiming another&amp;rsquo;s work to be one&amp;rsquo;s own. Other assessments (including ANGEL-administered quizzes and assessments as well as homework assignments) are expected to represent your own independent work unless specifically stated otherwise. Failure to comply will lead to sanctions against the student in accordance with the Policy on Academic Integrity in the Eberly College of Science. The Eberly College of Science Code of Mutual Respect and Cooperation (www.science.psu.edu/climate/Code-of-Mutual-Respect-final.pdf) embodies the values that we hope our faculty, staff, and students possess and will endorse to make The Eberly College of Science a place where every individual feels respected and valued, as well as challenged and rewarded.   The Eberly College of Science is committed to the academic success of students enrolled in the College&amp;rsquo;s  courses and undergraduate programs. When in need of help, students can utilize various College and University wide resources for learning assistance (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.science.psu.edu/advising/success&#34;&gt;http://www.science.psu.edu/advising/success&lt;/a&gt;). Penn State welcomes students with disabilities into the University&amp;rsquo;s educational programs. If you have a disability-related need for reasonable academic adjustments in this course, contact the Office for Disability Services (ODS) at 814-863-1807 (V/TTY). For further information regarding ODS, please visit the Office for Disability Services Web site at &lt;a href=&#34;http://equity.psu.edu/ods/.  &#34;&gt;http://equity.psu.edu/ods/.  &lt;/a&gt; In order to receive consideration for course accommodations, you must contact ODS and provide documentation (see the &lt;a href=&#34;http://equity.psu.edu/student-disability-resources/guidelines&#34;&gt;documentation guidelines&lt;/a&gt;). If the documentation supports the need for academic adjustments, ODS will provide a letter identifying appropriate academic adjustments. Please share this letter and discuss the adjustments with your instructor as early in the course as possible. You must contact ODS and request academic adjustment letters at the beginning of each semester.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>