<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>BMMB 554 | 2018</title>
    <link>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/</link>
    <description>Recent content on BMMB 554 | 2018</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Anton Nekrutenko | 2018 | CC-BY</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Syllabus</title>
      <link>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/about/</guid>
      <description>When &amp;amp; Where Mondays and Wednesdays | 2:30pm | Thomas 120
Instructor Anton Nekrutenko
aun1@psu.edu
Wartik 505
Office hours by appointment only
 IMPORTANT:  When contacting instructor use the above e-mail and include &amp;ldquo;BMMB554&amp;rdquo; in the subject line (you can simply click on e-mail address above as Subject already filled in there).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding DNA/Protein interactions</title>
      <link>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/topic14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/topic14/</guid>
      <description>An overview of ChIP seq  This material is based on a variety of sources acknowledged throughout this document. It follows the logic of a comprehensive overview of ChIP-seq methodology compiled by Shaun Mahony at Penn State.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing</title>
      <link>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/writing/</guid>
      <description>Writing is hard! Writing simply is harder! 
But there are great resources! Below are links to one such resource:
 The Title Says It All The Abstract and the Elevator Talk: A Tale of Two Summaries &amp;ldquo;It was a cold and rainy night&amp;rdquo;: Set the Scene with a Good Introduction Who, What, When, Where, How, and Why: The Ingredients in the Recipe for a Successful Methods Section Show Your Cards: The Results Section and the Poker Game If an IRDAM Journal Is What You Choose, Then Sequential Results Are What You Use Put Your Best Figure Forward: Line Graphs and Scattergrams Bars and Pies Make Better Desserts than Figures (also see this) Bring Your Best to the Table The Discussion Section: Your Closing Argument Giving Credit: Citations and References How to Write a Rave Review Top 10 Tips for Responding to Reviewer and Editor Comments Passing the Paternit&amp;eacute; Test (also see this)  Also see:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reference-based RNA-seq</title>
      <link>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/topic11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/topic11/</guid>
      <description>RNAseq: Reference-based  This tutorial is inspired by an exceptional RNAseq course at the Weill Cornell Medical College compiled by Friederike Dündar, Luce Skrabanek, and Paul Zumbo and by tutorials produced by Björn Grüning (@bgruening) for Freiburg Galaxy instance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diploid variant calling</title>
      <link>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/topic8/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/topic8/</guid>
      <description>Today we hear a lot about personalized medicine. Yet the personalization is defined by the genetic make up of the individual. Today we will discuss how this information can be uncovered from the genomic sequencing data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First analysis</title>
      <link>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/topic_docker2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/topic_docker2/</guid>
      <description>Our first actual analysis            Trajectories for the four teams in this class:       Team 1 Team 2 Team 3 Team 4     10.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diving into analyses</title>
      <link>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/topic_docker/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/topic_docker/</guid>
      <description>Setting up Jupyter For our analyses we will be using Jupyter. The problem is that everyone in this class has a different computer setup, which may cause issues with running Jupyter.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Variant calling: Pooled and Haploid systems</title>
      <link>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/topic9/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/topic9/</guid>
      <description>The majority of life on Earth is non-diploid and represented by prokaryotes, viruses and their derivatives such as our own mitochondria or plant&amp;rsquo;s chloroplasts. In non-diploid systems allele frequencies can range anywhere between 0 and 100% and there could be multiple (not just two) alleles per locus.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NGS data: Practicalities</title>
      <link>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/topic7/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/topic7/</guid>
      <description>In this section we will look at practical aspects of manipulation of next-generation sequencing data. We will start with Fastq format produced by most sequencing machines and will finish with SAM/BAM format representing mapped reads.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Python: The very first try</title>
      <link>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/python1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/python1/</guid>
      <description>Today we will have an introduction to Python - a general purpose programming language. We will do this by relying on two great resources:
   Software Carpentry Jupyter          Setting up you screen Open the following browser windows:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aligning many sequences quickly</title>
      <link>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/topic5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/topic5/</guid>
      <description>Speeding things up The topics we discussed in the past lecture explain fundamental concepts behind analysis of biological sequences. Today, we will be talking about algorithms that allow aligning billions of sequencing reads against reference genomes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sequence alignment: Introductory concepts</title>
      <link>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/topic3/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/topic3/</guid>
      <description>The cover image shows pairwise alignments for human, mouse, and dog KIF3 locus from Dubchak et al. 2000.
Introduction to dynamic programming (Based on dynamic programming example from InteractivePython).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assembly basics</title>
      <link>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/topic12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/topic12/</guid>
      <description>Genome assembly is a difficult task. In trying to explain it I will be relying on two highly regarded sources:
 Ben Langmead&amp;rsquo;s Teaching Materials Pevzner and Compeau Bioinformatics Book.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DNA Sequencing: PabBio, ONT and others</title>
      <link>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/topic2_3/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/topic2_3/</guid>
      <description>PacBio Single Molecule Sequencing PacBio is a fundamentally different approach to DNA sequencing as it allows reading single molecules. Thus it is an example is so called Single Molecule Sequencing or SMS.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DNA Sequencing: Illumina</title>
      <link>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/topic2_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/topic2_2/</guid>
      <description>A few classical papers to start In a series of now classical papersp Philip Green and co-workers has developed a quantitative framework for the analysis of data generated by automated DNA sequencers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DNA Sequencing: From Sanger to 454</title>
      <link>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/topic2_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/topic2_1/</guid>
      <description>The 50s, 60s and the 70s The difficulty with sequencing nucleic acids is nicely summarized by Hutchinson:2007:
  The chemical properties of different DNA molecules were so similar that it appeared difficult to separate them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>History</title>
      <link>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/topic1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/posts/topic1/</guid>
      <description>Why history? Knowing history is essential for understanding how we arrived to the current state of affairs in our field. It is also full of accidental discoveries and dramatic relationships making it quite interesting to read about.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Syllabus</title>
      <link>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/syllabus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nekrut.github.io/BMMB554/syllabus/</guid>
      <description>Instructor Anton Nekrutenko
aun1@psu.edu
Wartik 505
Office hours by appointment only
 &amp;#9888; When contacting instructor use the above e-mail and include &amp;ldquo;BMMB554&amp;rdquo; in the subject line (simply click on e-mail address).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>